[Emperor of Ye]
[إمبراطور يه الكبرى]
Prince Qi, please come with me.
يا أمير تشي، تفضل معي
Your Majesty, Xiao Wuyi campaigned in the Northern Border,
جلالتك، لقد قاد شياو وو يي الحملة إلى الشمال
repelled Northern Qin, and recaptured five cities.
وهزم جيش تشين الشمالية وانتزع خمس مدن
He is a man of merit.
إنه صاحب فضل
Killing him
إن قتلتَه
would only sadden our friends and gladden our enemies.
ألن يؤلم هذا أحباءنا ويسعد أعداءنا؟
Please show mercy, Your Majesty.
أرجو من جلالتك العفو عنه
Mother was right.
ما قالته أمي الإمبراطورة صحيح أيضا
An emperor cannot allow
عرش الإمبراطور
another power to exist at his side.
لا يقبل أن ينازعه فيه أحد
It seems tonight
يبدو أن هذه الليلة
will be another bloodbath.
ستكون ليلة دموية أخرى
I am willing to vouch for Young Lord Xiao.
أنا مستعد لضمان ولي العهد شياو
You're just a prince.
أنت مجرد أمير تشي
What gives you the right to vouch for him?
بأي حق تضمنه؟
Wuyi is my best
وو يي هو أفضل أصدقائي
and only friend.
وهو صديقي الوحيد
He will listen to me.
سيستمع إلى كلامي
Please give me a chance, Your Majesty.
أتوسل إلى جلالتك أن تمنحني فرصة
I will persuade Wuyi to withdraw his troops.
سأقنع وو يي بسحب قواته
And please keep Xiao Wuyi
وأرجو من جلالتك حماية شياو وو يي
and Prince Jing'an's Mansion safe, Your Majesty.
وحماية قصر أمير جينغآن
Grand Tutor.
أيها المعلم الأكبر
You were indeed right.
لقد كنت على حق
Prince Qi is the only perfect solution for tonight.
أمير تشي هو الحل الوحيد الذي يرضي جميع الأطراف الليلة
Just do as you said.
لنفعل كما قلت
Yes, Your Majesty.
أمرك يا جلالتك
Your Highness,
يا صاحب السمو
from now on, there won't be Yaoyao anymore.
من الآن فصاعدا، لم يعد هناك جيا يوي
The peace of the world and the survival of the royal clan
سلام البلاد وبقاء الأسرة الإمبراطورية
all depend on you alone, Your Highness.
كلاهما معلقان بسموك وحدك
[Key to the Phoenix Heart]
[مفتاح قلب العنقاء]
[Episode 4]
[الحلقة الرابعة]
All I want is peace across the realm.
كل ما أريده هو السلام في العالم
Are you willing to grant that?
الإمبراطورة الأرملة، هل ستعطينني إياه؟
Your Highness,
يا سيدي الأمير
rebellions in the capital have all been quelled.
تم قمع جميع التمردات في العاصمة
The troops have assembled.
واجتمعت القوات
We can enter the palace at any time.
وهي على أهبة الاستعداد لدخول القصر
Wait for news from Wuyi.
لننتظر أخبار وو يي
Yes.
أمرك
One hundred thousand Beifu soldiers
مئة ألف جندي من جيش الشمال
are just outside the city now.
يرابطون خارج المدينة
I have already said,
لقد قلت من قبل
as long as you hand over your military power,
طالما أنك مستعد لتسليم السلطة العسكرية
I can restore peace to the world.
فسأعيد السلام إلى البلاد
I can also promise you
ويمكنني أيضا أن أعدك
to erect a monument for the 30,000 soldiers who died in vain.
ببناء نصب تذكاري للثلاثين ألف جندي الذين ماتوا ظلما
But if you refuse to hand over your military power,
أما إذا رفضتَ تسليم سلطتك العسكرية
I will have to be ruthless.
فلن يكون أمامي خيار سوى القسوة عليك
So what if the Beifu soldiers are just outside the wall?
لا تقل إن جيش الشمال يقف خلف الأسوار
You, Young Lord Xiao, have already fallen into my trap.
أنت يا ولي العهد شياو قد وقعت بالفعل في فخي
They cannot save you.
لن يتمكنوا من إنقاذك
I'll just say Prince Changsha killed Young Lord Xiao.
سأقول إن أمير تشانغشا هو من قتل ولي العهد شياو
What can your Beifu soldiers
فماذا يمكن لجيشك الشمالي
do to me?
أن يفعل ضدي حينها؟
His Highness Prince Qi has arrived!
وصل سمو أمير تشي
Why aren't Mao and Lejun here yet?
لماذا لم يصل ماو وله جيون بعد؟
Shouldn't they have left the city long ago?
أليس من المفترض أن يغادرا المدينة منذ فترة؟
My Lady,
يا آنستي
did you hear any fighting in the city when we left?
هل سمعتِ أصوات قتال عند مغادرة المدينة؟
Fighting?
أصوات قتال؟
Why do I feel that when we left the city,
لماذا أشعر أننا حين غادرنا المدينة
I didn't even see a soul?
لم أرَ حتى ظلَّ أحد؟
Cang'er, did you hear it?
تسانغ أر، هل سمعتِ شيئا؟
I didn't either.
أنا لم أسمع أيضا
Then perhaps I misheard.
ربما أكون قد أسأت السمع
Could something have happened to Mao and Lejun?
هل يُعقل أن مكروها قد أصاب ماو وله جيون؟
Let's go back first.
من الأفضل أن نعود أولاً
If we go back now,
إذا عدنا الآن
wouldn't we be walking right into a trap?
أليست كإلقاء أنفسنا في الشرك؟
Let's wait a bit longer.
لننتظر قليلا
No one said a carriage was prepared.
لم يخبرني أحد بأنه تم إعداد عربة
My Lady, Her Highness ordered that
يا آنستي، لدى الأميرة أمر لكِ
[Shadow Envoy]
[مبعوث الظل]
you must leave with me immediately.
يرجى المغادرة معي على الفور
Here is the letter.
هذه هي الرسالة
Mother's private seal?
هذا ختم أمي الخاص
[Go now]
[غادري بسرعة]
But I have to wait for Mao.
لكن يجب أن أنتظر ماو
Prince Qi has already entered the palace. He can't come.
أمير تشي دخل القصر بالفعل ولن يتمكن من المجيء
Why did he enter the palace?
لماذا دخل القصر؟
There's no time to explain.
لا وقت للشرح
My Lady, please leave quickly.
يا آنستي، أرجوكِ غادري بسرعة
Father?
أبي
Yaoyao,
جيا يوي
I'm here to take you back to the city.
جئت لأعيدك إلى المدينة
My Lord,
سيدي
Her Highness wants My Lady to leave.
الأميرة تأمر الآنسة بالرحيل
Mind your own business!
لا شأن لك
I won't go with you.
لن أذهب معك
I will not marry Xiao Wuyi.
لن أتزوج شياو وو يي
I'm leaving with Mao.
أريد أن أغادر مع ماو
By His Majesty's order:
بأمر من جلالة الإمبراطور
I have learned that Prince Changsha has committed treason and besieged the palace.
علمنا أن أمير تشانغشا تمرد وحاصر القصر
Such fratricide
وأن الإخوة يقتتلون
pains me deeply.
وهذا يحزننا بشدة
[Xuanzheng Hall]
[قصر شيوان تشنغ]
Fortunately, Prince Qi was astute
لحسن الحظ، كان الأمير تشي فطناً
and reported it.
واكتشف الأمر وأبلغنا به
With Young Lord Xiao of Prince Jing'an's Mansion,
ودخل القصر مع ولي العهد شياو من قصر أمير جينغآن
he entered the palace to quell the rebellion.
لقمع التمرد
I am deeply comforted.
وقد سرَّنا ذلك كثيرًا
His Majesty is awake?
استيقظ جلالته
When?
متى استيقظ؟
His Majesty has another edict:
صدر أمر آخر من جلالته
I am prone to illness.
أنا ضعيف الجسد وكثير المرض
Prince Qi, Li Mao, is wise and perceptive,
الأمير تشي، لي ماو، حكيم وذكي
resembling me greatly.
ويشبهني كثيرًا
He is hereby ordered to enter the Eastern Palace
ولذا أمرنا بإقامته في القصر الشرقي
and serve as Regent.
ليتولى إدارة شؤون البلاد
Where is His Majesty?
أين جلالته الآن؟
Appointing a Regent is of utmost importance.
إدارة البلاد أمر في غاية الأهمية
How could it be handled so hastily?
كيف يمكن حسمه بهذه السطحية؟
Your Majesty.
الإمبراطورة الأرملة
His Majesty said,
قال جلالته
"I understand Mother's intentions,
إنني أعلم بنوايا أمي الإمبراطورة
but worldly affairs must follow their natural course.
لكن أمور البلاد يجب أن تسير بطبيعتها
Forcing them will only backfire."
أما فرض الأمور بالقوة، فلن يؤدي إلى الخير
Does His Majesty know
هل يعلم جلالته
that releasing Xiao Wuyi
أن إطلاق سراح شياو وو يي
is like letting a tiger return to the mountain?
يعني إطلاق نمر إلى الجبال
I didn't hesitate to get my hands dirty
لا أبالي بأن تتسخ يداي
to eliminate Xiao Wuyi.
وسأقضي على شياو وو يي
This wasn't just for His Majesty,
هذا ليس من أجل جلالته فقط
but to permanently remove a threat to Ye.
بل من أجل القضاء على الخطر عن يه الكبرى إلى الأبد
What is His Majesty doing?
ماذا يفعل جلالته؟
"No egg stays intact in an overturned nest."
إذا انهار العش فلن ينجو أحد
Ye cannot survive without Xiao Wuyi now.
لا تستطيع يه الكبرى اليوم الاستغناء عن شياو وو يي
Tonight, Prince Changsha committed treason and besieged the palace.
تمرد أمير تشانغشا وحاصر القصر الليلة
Prince Qi and Young Lord Xiao quelled the rebellion together.
وقمع أمير تشي وولي العهد شياو التمرد معًا
His Highness appreciated Prince Qi's loyalty and bravery,
جلالته يقدر ولاء وشجاعة أمير تشي
and has appointed him as Regent.
وقد عينه وصيا على العرش
Impossible.
مستحيل
The imperial edict has been issued.
لقد صدر المرسوم الإمبراطوري
His Highness and Princess Pingning have entered the Eastern Palace.
دخل سموه وأميرة بينغنينغ إلى القصر الشرقي
As for you, Yaoyao,
أما أنتِ يا جيا يوي
you must marry into Prince Jing'an's Mansion tonight.
فعليكِ الليلة الزواج من قصر أمير جينغآن
Prince Qi, receive the edict.
يا أمير تشي، تفضل بقبول المرسوم
You want to ensure the coexistence of Xiao Wuyi and the Empress Dowager,
تريد حماية شياو وو يي والإمبراطورة الأرملة معا
and the coexistence of Beifu soldiers and the Li family's empire.
وحماية جيش الشمال وعائلة لي الإمبراطورية معا
So today,
إذًا اليوم
no matter what edict I issue,
مهما كان المرسوم الذي أصدره
are you willing to stand with Xiao Wuyi,
هل أنت مستعد لمشاركة شياو وو يي
through fortune and misfortune,
في السراء والضراء
and share life and death?
وفي الحياة والموت؟
She is still waiting for you.
إنها ما زالت تنتظرك
Come.
هيا
Wuyi.
وو يي
Tonight, are you really going to...
هل أنت حقا ستفعل ذلك الليلة؟
Think carefully.
فكر جيدا
If you receive this edict...
إذا قبلت هذا المرسوم
you will never be able to leave Jiankang Palace in your life.
فلن تتمكن من مغادرة قصر جيانكانغ طوال حياتك
No matter who wins today,
بغض النظر عمن سيفوز أو يخسر اليوم
the world will be thrown into chaos.
ستقع البلاد في فوضى عارمة
Wuyi.
وو يي
I have experienced war since I was a child.
لقد عشت الحروب منذ طفولتي
I know what kind of hell it is.
وأعرف جيدًا كيف يكون ذلك الجحيم
My Lady, go!
يا آنستي، اذهبي بسرعة
Go!
اذهبي بسرعة
Cang'er!
تسانغ أر
Yaoyao.
جيا يوي
Father.
أبي
Listen to me.
استمعي لكلامي
Run, My Lady!
يا آنستي، اهربي
Cang'er!
تسانغ أر
Xie Jiayu!
شيه جيا يوي
Are you going to listen to me?
ألن تستمعي لكلام أبيكِ؟
Please don't kill her!
لا تقتلها
I'll go with you!
سأذهب معك
Why did your shoe fall off?
كيف سقط حذاؤك؟
Come, let me put it on for you.
تعالي، سأساعدك في ارتدائه
A bride must be beautiful.
العروس يجب أن تكون جميلة
I thought you
لقد ظننت أن أبي
were a gentleman admired by everyone.
رجل نبيل يحترمه الجميع
I've never seen you kill anyone.
لم أرك تقتل أحدا من قبل
Why?
لماذا؟
Why did you do this?
لماذا تفعل هذا؟
Don't cry.
لا تبكي
Yaoyao,
جيا يوي
you should grow up now.
لقد حان وقت نضجكِ
The first thing you learn when you grow up is that
وأول درس ستتعلمينه بعد أن تكبري هو
sometimes, you have no choice.
أن المرء لا يملك خياراً دائما
Mao had no choice.
ماو هكذا
And so do you.
وأنتِ كذلك
I thought you loved me the most.
كنت أظن أنك تحبني أكثر من أي شخص آخر
Everyone has a scale in their heart,
لكل شخص ميزان في قلبه
weighing what is important and what is more important.
يوازن فيه بين ما هو مهم وما هو أهم
So you must marry Xiao Wuyi.
لذلك، يجب عليكِ الزواج من شياو وو يي
Is... Is it for the Xie family?
هل هذا من أجل عائلة شيه؟
Take her away.
خذوها
Father! Tell me the reason!
أبي، أخبرني بالسبب
Why must I marry Xiao Wuyi?
لماذا يجب عليّ الزواج من شياو وو يي؟
Why?
لماذا؟
You will be happier if you don't know.
ستكونين أسعد إذا لم تعرفي
I want to know.
أريد أن أعرف
It's for Mao.
من أجل ماو
Prince Jing'an's Mansion commands the Beifu Army of 200,000 soldiers.
قصر أمير جينغآن يسيطر على مائتي ألف جندي من جيش الشمال
They're ambitious
وطموحهم كبير
and can change the dynasty at any time.
ويمكنهم تغيير السلالة الحاكمة في أي وقت
But why haven't they done it yet?
ولكن لماذا لم يفعلوا ذلك بعد؟
Because there are noble families
لأن هناك أسرًا عريقة
like our Xie family,
مثل عائلتي، عائلة شيه
supporting His Highness—
تدعم سمو الأمير
or you can say supporting the Li royal family.
أو بعبارة أخرى، تدعم عشيرة لي الإمبراطورية
So even if the Xiao family takes the throne,
لذلك، حتى لو اعتلت عائلة شياو العرش
they won't be able to sit securely on it.
فلن يستقر لها الحكم
But you never wanted to associate with the Xiao family.
لكن يا أبي، لم تكن يومًا ترغب في التحالف مع عائلة شياو
If I run away from the wedding now
ولو هربت من الزواج الآن
and break ties with them,
وقطعت علاقتنا به
wouldn't that be better?
ألن يكون ذلك أفضل؟
Maybe we could have done that before,
ربما كان ذلك ممكنًا في السابق
but now the Regent is Mao.
لكن ماو أصبح الآن وصيًا على العرش
If Prince Jing'an's Mansion has rebellious intentions,
فإن راود قصر أمير جينغآن أي طموح للتمرد
Mao, as the Regent,
فلن تكون أمام ماو، بصفته الوصي
will have no way to survive.
أي فرصة للنجاة
For Mao,
من أجل ماو
for the Xie family,
ومن أجل عائلة شيه
you must be this pawn.
لا بد أن تكوني هذه القطعة في اللعبة
Father,
أبي
I don't seem to know you anymore.
أشعر أنني لم أعد أعرفك
Because...
لأن
it's time for you to grow up.
لقد حان وقت نضجكِ
All troops, heed my command!
أيها الجيش، استمعوا للأوامر
Greetings, Father.
تحياتي لك يا أبي الأمير
Prince Jing'an, Xiao Ju,
أمير جينغآن، شياو جيوي
and the Heir of Prince Jing'an, Xiao Wuyi,
ولي عهد أمير جينغآن، شياو وو يي
receive the imperial decree.
تفضلا بتلقي المرسوم
Prince Changsha has committed treason,
أمير تشانغشا قد تمرد
and his crime is punishable by death.
وجريمته تستوجب الإعدام
The Xiaos received the decree to mobilize the Beifu Army to suppress the rebellion.
قاد الأب والابن من عائلة شياو جيش الشمال لقمع التمرد
Their loyalty is commendable,
وولاؤهما يستحق الثناء
and We are very pleased.
وقد سرَّنا ذلك كثيرًا
I hereby appoint Xiao Ju as Grand General of National Defense,
يُعين شياو جيوي جنرالاً عاما لحماية الدولة
and Young Lord Xiao as General of National Support.
ويُعين ولي العهد شياو جنرالا مساعدا للدولة
Young Lord Xiao is ordered to...
ويؤمر ولي العهد شياو
To marry the daughter of the Xie family.
بإتمام زواجه من ابنة عائلة شيه
The Beifu Army must return immediately
على جيش الشمال العودة إلى الحدود فورا
without delay.
دون أي تأخير
Yes, Your Majesty.
أمتثل للأمر
Furthermore, Prince Changsha deployed military equipment without authorization,
كما أن أمير تشانغشا حرك العتاد العسكري سرا
causing the innocent deaths of Beifu soldiers.
مما تسبب في تضحية جنود جيش الشمال الأبرياء
I am deeply pained.
وهذا يؤلم قلبنا بشدة
Prince Changsha's private properties shall be confiscated
لذا تُصادر جميع ممتلكاته الخاصة لتعويض أسر الجنود
A Monument of Loyalty shall be erected and recorded in history
ويُقام نصب الولاء والوفاء لحماية الأمة ويُسجل في كتب التاريخ
to honor the loyalty of the Beifu soldiers.
لتخليد وفاء جنود جيش الشمال وولائهم
Thank you, Your Majesty, for your great grace.
شكرًا لجلالتكم على هذا الفضل العظيم
Wuyi,
وو يي
you have sought justice
لقد استعدتَ الحق للجنود
for the soldiers who died in vain.
الذين ماتوا ظلما
As for what happened tonight...
ما حدث الليلة
I know.
أنا أعلم
She...
أما هي
Don't worry about her.
فلا تقلق
Tell her to wait for me.
أخبرها أن تنتظرني
I will find a way.
سأجد حلا
Alright.
حسنا
I will pass it on to her.
سأنقل لها رسالتك
But there's something I want to ask you.
لكن هناك أمر أود أن أسألك عنه
Who brought you back tonight?
من الذي أعادك الليلة؟
It was Master.
إنه معلمي
The Grand Tutor?
المعلم الأكبر؟
What's wrong?
هل هناك خطب ما؟
Nothing.
لا شيء
General Xiao,
أيها الجنرال العجوز شياو
Prince Qi, Young Lord Xiao.
أمير تشي وولي العهد شياو
Regarding the rebellion tonight,
اضطرابات الليلة
Young Lord Xiao, thank you for your bravery and righteousness
ولي العهد شياو، لولا شجاعتك الليلة
in saving the people from suffering
لما نجا الناس من المحنة
and rescuing the court from imminent peril.
ولما أُنقذ البلاط من الكارثة
The Empress Dowager specially ordered me to thank you
لقد أمرتني الإمبراطورة الأرملة أن أشكرك
for saving our lives on behalf of
بالنيابة عن المسؤولين
all the officials and the people of the realm.
وبالنيابة عن شعب البلاد على إنقاذك لحياتهم
Son.
يا بني
What were you and Prince Qi silently communicating with each other?
ما هذه الألغاز التي تتبادلها مع أمير تشي؟
After tonight,
بعد هذه الليلة
Yizhi won't just be Prince Qi anymore.
لن يكون يي تشي مجرد أمير تشي
He will also be the Regent.
بل سيصبح أيضًا وصيا على العرش
What?
ماذا؟
Father,
أبي الملك
I'll...
أنا
go for a walk alone.
أريد أن أتمشى بمفردي
I have brought Jiayu back.
لقد أعدتُ جيا يوي
Congratulations, Young Lord Xiao,
أهنئك يا ولي العهد شياو
for seeking justice for the soldiers who died in vain.
لتحقيقك العدالة للجنود الذين ماتوا ظلماً
You played the Empty City Stratagem beautifully.
خطة المدينة الفارغة هذه كانت رائعة
I'm impressed.
إنني معجب بك
Grand Tutor, why don't you
ماذا تقصد أيها المعلم الأكبر؟
just speak your mind?
تفضل وقلها بصراحة
The Beifu Army brought back by the Old Prince
جيش الشمال الذي أعاده الأمير العجوز
is at most 10,000 men.
لا يتجاوز عشرة آلاف جندي
If they had really fought the Imperial Guards tonight,
لو اندلع قتال حقيقي الليلة مع الحرس الإمبراطوري
the outcome would be unknown.
لما كانت النتيجة مضمونة
Am I right?
تخميني صحيح، أليس كذلك؟
Yizhi said
قال يي تشي
that he was also escorted back by you tonight.
إنك أنت من أعدته إلى القصر الليلة
Grand Tutor, you never planned to let them go, did you?
لم تكن تنوي أن تدعهم يرحلون أبدا أليس كذلك؟
Now the royal family is in decline,
لقد ضعفت الأسرة الإمبراطورية اليوم
His Majesty is prone to illness,
وجلالة الإمبراطور مريض
and the Empress Dowager is dictatorial and incompetent.
والإمبراطورة الأرملة مستبدة وضعيفة
Our Southern Ye is on the verge of collapse.
وأصبحت يه الجنوبية على شفا الانهيار
Since there is no absolute winner,
بما أنه لا يوجد فائز مطلق
it's better to have a win-win situation
فمن الأفضل إيجاد حل يرضي الطرفين
and make Prince Qi the Regent.
بتعيين أمير تشي وصيا على العرش
For you
هذا بالنسبة لك يا ولي العهد شياو
and the realm,
وبالنسبة للبلاد
isn't it a good thing?
أليس جيداً؟
You cultivated Yizhi for years
يا معلم أكبر، رعيت يي تشي لسنوات عديدة
just for today?
هل كل ذلك من أجل هذا اليوم؟
In Prince Qi,
في أمير تشي
I saw hope.
أرى الأمل
What about your daughter?
وماذا عن ابنتك؟
Everyone in the city says the Grand Tutor spoils his daughter the most,
يقول كل من في المدينة إنك تدلل ابنتك كثيرا
but I think you are just too cruel.
لكنني أرى أن قلبك شديد القسوة
You separated Yizhi and your daughter
لقد فرقت بين يي تشي وابنتك
just to plant a seed of suspicion
أليس هدفك أن تزرع بذرة الشك
between Yizhi and me, didn't you?
بيني وبين يي تشي؟
What do you mean by that?
ماذا تعني بكلامك هذا؟
You asked
هذا الزواج
the Empress Dowager for this marriage yourself,
أنت من طلبته من الإمبراطورة الأرملة
didn't you?
أليس كذلك؟
As for abandoning Jiayu,
أما التخلي عن جيا يوي
that was Prince Qi's own choice.
فقد كان اختيار أمير تشي نفسه
You can't blame anyone.
لا يمكنكما لوم أي شخص
Yes,
نعم
but I feel sad for them.
لكنني أشعر بالأسف من أجلهما
I did it for the realm.
ما فعلته كان من أجل البلاد
I have a clear conscience.
وضميري مرتاح تماما
From tonight on,
بدءا من الليلة
Yizhi is the Regent,
سيصبح يي تشي وصياً على العرش
and Xie Jiayu is my Secondary Consort.
وستكون شيه جيا يوي محظيتي
I hope you stop here, Grand Tutor.
آمل أن تتوقف عند هذا الحد أيها المعلم الأكبر
But now the Regent is Mao.
لكن ماو أصبح الآن وصيًا على العرش
If Prince Jing'an's Mansion has rebellious intentions,
فإن راود قصر أمير جينغآن أي طموح للتمرد
Mao, as the Regent,
فلن تكون أمام ماو، بصفته الوصي
will have no way to survive.
أي فرصة للنجاة
For Mao,
من أجل ماو
for the Xie family,
ومن أجل عائلة شيه
you must be this pawn.
لا بد أن تكوني هذه القطعة في اللعبة
Cang'er!
تسانغ أر
Darling, you're not asleep yet?
ألم تنامي بعد يا سيدتي؟
Tonight in the capital,
الليلة في العاصمة
the wind is howling and the rain is pouring.
الرياح قوية والأمطار غزيرة
Lord Xie,
يا سيد شيه
was the road easy to travel?
هل كان الطريق سالكًا؟
There is no wind or rain.
أي رياح وأمطار؟
It did rain a little just now.
لقد هطل القليل من المطر للتو
The rain stopped.
وقد توقف
The sky has cleared up.
والسماء صافية الآن
Where is Yaoyao?
أين جيا يوي؟
Tonight is Yaoyao's wedding night.
اليوم هو ليلة زفاف جيا يوي
Naturally, she is at Prince Jing'an's Mansion.
بالطبع هي في قصر أمير جينغآن
But if you miss her,
لكن إن اشتقتِ إليها
you can see her again when she returns in three days.
فسترينها بعد ثلاثة أيام عندما تعود لزيارة أهلها
You killed
لقد قتلت
the secret guard I sent to protect Yaoyao?
الحراس السريين الذين أرسلتهم لحماية جيا يوي
I don't understand what you are saying, Darling.
لا أفهم ما الذي تتحدثين عنه
Fine.
حسنًا
Then I will say something you can understand, My Lord.
سأتحدث بما تفهمه إذن
Your son has become the Regent.
لقد أصبح ابنك وصيًا على العرش
Are you satisfied now, My Lord?
هل أنت راضٍ الآن يا سيدي؟
I am thirsty.
أشعر بالعطش
I'll go get a cup of tea.
سأذهب لأسكب كوبًا من الشاي أولًا
Lord Xie.
يا سيد شيه
That Li Mao, your illegitimate child with Consort An
ابنك غير الشرعي من المحظية آن للإمبراطور السابق
of the Late Emperor,
المدعو لي ماو
was finally pushed into the position of Regent by you.
أخيراً قمت بتنصيبه وصياً على العرش
After years of painstaking efforts,
بعد سنوات من التخطيط
you have finally made it tonight.
نجحت الليلة
My Lord,
يا سيدي
are you satisfied?
هل أنت راضٍ؟
Are you looking at the Grand Tutor's Mansion or the Prince Jing'an's Mansion?
هل تنظر إلى قصر المعلم الأكبر أم قصر أمير جينغآن؟
Tonight,
الليلة
you shouldn't have made this choice.
لم يكن ينبغي لك أن تختار هذا
I didn't choose.
لم أختر
It was just a stalling tactic.
إنها مجرد خطة لكسب الوقت
Wuyi and I will find a way.
سأجد أنا وو يي حلاً
Brother.
أخي
I think one day,
أشعر أنه سيأتي يوم
you will regret today's decision.
ستندم فيه على قرارك اليوم
Your Highness.
يا ولي العهد
Let her sleep in peace.
دعيها تنم بسلام
I won't go in tonight.
لن أدخل الليلة
Wait.
انتظر
Your Highness,
يا ولي العهد
it's your wedding night.
في ليلة زفافنا
Where are you going?
إلى أين أنت ذاهب؟
Xie Jiayu,
شيه جيا يوي
you want me to stay?
هل تريدين أن أبقى؟
Husband,
زوجي
it's our wedding night,
إنها ليلة زفافنا
and we haven't drunk the nuptial cup yet.
ولم نشرب كأس الزواج بعد
Don't worry. It's not poisoned.
اطمئن، ليس فيه سم
Xie Jiayu,
شيه جيا يوي
can you come up with some new tricks?
ألا تستطيعين استخدام حيل جديدة؟
Do you think I'm Qing Long?
أتظنين أنني تشينغ لونغ؟
Xiao Wuyi, let go of me!
شياو وو يي، اتركني
You treat me like this. Do you believe I'll...
عاملتني هكذا، هل تصدق
What?
أصدق ماذا؟
That your father will come and take you back?
هل أصدق أن والدك سيأتي ليعيدكِ؟
We've been busy all night
لقد انشغلتُ طوال الليلة
and haven't eaten.
ولم آكل شيئًا
Stop struggling,
توقفي عن المقاومة
or your hands will get hurt.
وإلا ستؤذين يديكِ
When you go crying to Yizhi,
وعندما تبكين أمام يي تشي
don't blame it on me.
لا تلوميني على ذلك
Yizhi?
يي تشي؟
You know Mao?
هل تعرف ماو؟
This is Mao's personal jade pendant.
هذه قلادة اليشم الخاصة بماو
Why do you have it?
كيف هي معك؟
What did you do to Mao?
ماذا فعلت بماو؟
I abducted him.
لقد قيدته
I snatched it.
وأخذتها منه بالقوة
Hurry up and eat.
هيا، كُل
Why did you kick me?
لماذا ركلتني؟
Aren't you hungry after fighting all night?
ألا تشعر بالجوع بعد قتال طوال الليل؟
I don't know what you like to eat,
لا أعرف ما تحبين أن تأكلي عادةً
so I just grabbed some from the kitchen.
فأحضرتُ بعض الأطباق من المطبخ
Have a taste.
تذوقي
The lamb shoulder from our small kitchen is quite good.
كتف الضأن الذي يطهوه مطبخنا  لذيذ جدا
What's wrong?
ما الأمر؟
Nothing.
لا شيء
I just suddenly remembered
لقد تذكرت فجأة
that Cang'er used to love lamb.
أن تسانغ أر كانت تحب لحم الضأن كثيراً
Wait. I thought about it carefully,
لا، لقد فكرتُ في الأمر ملياً
and it seems to have gone too smoothly.
يبدو أن طريقي كان سهلاً جداً
You searched the whole city,
لقد فتشت في كل أنحاء المدينة
but no one found me.
ولم يكتشفني أحد
Then something happened in the palace.
ثم حدث أمر جلل في القصر
Then you went to the palace to suppress the rebellion,
ودخلت أنت لقمع التمرد
and Mao became the Regent.
وأصبح ماو وصياً على العرش
There must be something wrong.
هناك أمر مريب بالتأكيد
Keep analyzing.
تابعي تحليلكِ
Father said Prince Changsha besieged the palace,
قال أبي إن أمير تشانغشا حاصر القصر
Prince Qi and Young Lord Xiao entered the palace together to suppress the rebellion,
وأن أمير تشي وولي العهد شياو دخلا القصر معًا لإخماد التمرد
and His Majesty appointed Mao as Regent.
وجلالته عين ماو وصياً على العرش
But Mao clearly wanted to leave with me.
لكن ماو كان يريد الرحيل معي
And the map of the Prince Jing'an's Mansion...
بالإضافة إلى خريطة قصر أمير جينغآن
That was a military map,
إنها خريطة عسكرية
obviously drawn by a military man.
ومن الواضح أن من رسمها رجل عسكري
When Mao gave it to me,
عندما أعطاني إياها ماو
I felt something was wrong.
شعرت أن هناك شيئًا غريباً
This map...
هذه الخريطة
You drew this map?
أنت من رسمها
Not bad. You're not too stupid.
أحسنتِ، لستِ غبية تمامًا
You helped Mao and me escape?
إذن أنت من ساعدني وماو على الهرب
No, no.
لا، هذا غير صحيح
It's also possible that you pretended to help Mao,
ربما تظاهرت بمساعدة ماو
but in reality, you kidnapped him and took him to the palace,
لكنك في الحقيقة اختطفته إلى القصر
forcing him to become the Regent.
وأجبرته على أن يصبح الوصي
You even...
وأنت
Stop. Cut it out.
توقفي، كفى
I think you should stop analyzing.
من الأفضل أن تتوقفي عن التحليل
It's not impossible.
ولكن هذا الاحتمال ليس مستبعدًا
Mao is my best friend.
ماو هو أعز أصدقائي
Why would I force him
فلماذا أجبره
to do things he doesn't want to do?
على فعل شيء لا يريده؟
You are Mao's good friend,
أنتَ صديق ماو المقرب
yet you asked the Empress Dowager to have me marry you in court?
وطلبت الزواج مني أمام الإمبراطورة الأرملة
If I had known you two were...
لو كنت أعرف أمركما
I would have...
لكنت
Forget it.
انسي الأمر
"Pine and cypress stand firm in frost.
الجليد يختبر صمود الصنوبر
Wind and rain turn into dragon's roar.
والعواصف تطلق زئير التنين
So lofty ambitions
هكذا تظهر الطموحات العالية
reach the highest peak."
لتعتلي قمم الجبال الشاهقة
Have you heard this poem?
هل سمعتِ بهذه القصيدة من قبل؟
Mao wrote it.
كتبها ماو
Do you know who he wrote it for?
هل تعرفين لمن كتبها؟
You're not saying it was for you, are you?
لا تخبرني أنه كتبها لك
I knew him when we were nobodies,
عرفته عندما كنا نمر بظروف صعبة
much earlier than you did.
قبل أن تعرفيه بوقت طويل
You are sinister,
أنت رجل ماكر ومخادع
murderous,
يقتل بلا رحمة
cold-blooded, and lustful.
قاسي القلب وشهواني
Mao must have been deceived by your appearance.
بالتأكيد خُدع ماو بمظهرك الخارجي
That's why he...
لذلك هو
Sinister?
ماكر ومخادع
Murderous?
يقتل بلا رحمة
Cold-blooded and lustful?
قاسي القلب وشهواني
If he weren't my friend,
لولا أنه صديقي
you wouldn't have the chance to speak to me like this.
لما أُتيحت لكِ الفرصة للتحدث معي هكذا
I didn't expect Li Mao
أن يصبح لي ماو وصيًا على العرش
to become the Regent.
كان أمرًا خارج توقعاتي
It was a stopgap measure.
إنه مجرد إجراء مؤقت
The situation is unstable.
الوضع غير مستقر
He can't leave,
لن يستطيع الرحيل
and neither can you.
ولا أنتِ أيضًا
From this night on,
ابتداءً من الليلة
you, Xie Jiayu,
أنتِ شيه جيا يوي
shall be the Secondary Consort of the Heir of Prince Jing'an.
المحظية لولي عهد قصر أمير جينغآن
For Li Mao's sake,
من أجل لي ماو
you'd better behave yourself,
من الأفضل أن تلتزمي حدودك
playing your role well.
وكوني محظية جيدة لولي العهد
When the time is right,
وعندما يحين الوقت المناسب
I will arrange for you to meet.
سأرتب لكما لقاءً
Whether you're going to stay or leave,
أما البقاء أو الرحيل
we can talk about it after you meet.
فسيناقش بعد أن تلتقيا
Xiao Wuyi.
شياو وو يي
Are you really Li Mao's friend?
هل أنت حقًا صديق لي ماو؟
If you want me to believe you,
إذا أردتني أن أصدقك
take me out of the city tonight.
فخذني خارج المدينة الليلة
No.
لا
I am Xiao Wuyi, a murderous man.
أنا شياو وو يي سفّاك الدماء
So you'd better behave yourself
لذا من الأفضل أن تلتزمي حدودك
and stay put.
ولا تذهبي إلى أي مكان
-Your Highness.
ولي العهد -
Do you want some?
هل تأكل؟
Your Highness, is there something on your mind?
يا ولي العهد، هل يشغلك أمر ما؟
The Grand Tutor's appearance tonight was unexpected.
ظهور المعلم الأكبر الليلة كان مفاجئًا جدًا
How did you find out that the Young Master of Miraculous Craft
كيف اكتشفتما أن صاحبة اليد البارعة
was the one who designed the repeating crossbow?
هي مصممة القوس الآلي؟
After the incident at Jiuzhang Plain,
بعد الحادث في سهل جيوتشانغ
you ordered us to return to the capital immediately
أمرتنا بالعودة إلى العاصمة فورًا
to secretly investigate the Vice Minister in charge of weapons manufacturing.
للتحقيق سرا مع نائب المدير المسؤول عن صناعة الأسلحة
We found the blueprint of the repeating crossbow
وفي مكتب نائب مدير الخزانة وي
in Vice Minister Wei's study.
وجدنا مخطط تصميم القوس الآلي
That blueprint had the mark of the Young Master of Miraculous Craft.
وكان على ذلك المخطط علامة صاحبة اليد البارعة
So we followed the clues.
لذا تتبعنا هذا الخيط
Yes.
نعم
This Young Master of Miraculous Craft
هذه صاحبة اليد البارعة
is not hard to find in Jiankang.
ليس من الصعب العثور عليها في جيانكانغ
He's always been selling goods at Xiyue Restaurant.
كانت تبيع بضائعها دائمًا في مطعم شي يوه
Although he doesn't have a fixed stall or shop,
ورغم أنها لم تكن تملك متجرا أو كشكا ثابتا
he is very close to the owner of Xiyue Restaurant.
إلا أنها على علاقة جيدة بصاحب مطعم شي يوه
So, under the guise of doing business,
لذلك، تظاهرنا بأننا نريد عقد صفقة تجارية
we asked the owner to invite him out.
ورتبنا للقاءها عن طريق صاحب مطعم شي يوه
And that was how you caught Xie Jiayu?
ثم قبضنا على شيه جيا يوي
This three-foot, four-arrow repeating crossbow
هذا القوس الآلي ذو الثلاثة أقدام والأربعة سهام
was custom-made for a buyer.
صُنع خصيصًا لأحد المشترين
His surname is...
لقبه
Xiao.
شياو
And his given name is Sheng.
واسمه الشخصي هو شنغ
But we found out that Xie Jiayu didn't know anything about it.
لكنكما اكتشفتما أن شيه جيا يوي لم تكن على علم بذلك
Your Highness, is there something wrong?
يا ولي العهد، هل هناك خطب ما؟
Nothing is wrong.
لا شيء خاطئ
It's just that all of this
لكن كل هذا
went a bit too smoothly.
يسير بسلاسة مفرطة
The Empress Dowager has lived deep in the palace for a long time.
الإمبراطورة الأرملة تقيم في القصر منذ زمن
How could she know that there was a
فكيف عرفت بوجود صاحبة اليد البارعة
Young Master of Miraculous Craft in Jiankang,
في مدينة جيانكانغ؟
and even know what she could
وعرفت ما الذي تستطيع تصميمه
and couldn't design?
وما الذي لا تستطيع تصميمه؟
There must be some connection here
لا بد أن هناك
that we don't know about.
صلة ما لا نعرفها
I hope it's not what I suspect.
آمل ألا يكون الأمر كما توقعت
Then I will continue to investigate Xiyue Restaurant.
إذًا سأواصل التحقيق في مطعم شي يوه
Investigate?
التحقيق
It's too slow.
بطيء جدًا
My Lady.
يا آنستي
Actually, I think
في الحقيقة، في رأيي
Young Lord Xiao and his 2 guards
إن ولي العهد شياو وحارسيه
are not as scary as rumors say.
ليسوا مخيفين كما يُقال عنهم
Don't believe everything he says.
لا تصدقي كل ما يقوله
Did you forget what happened at Xiyue Restaurant and the ferry?
أنسيتِ ما حدث في مطعم شي يوه والميناء؟
So you mean...
إذن تقصدين يا آنستي
Who knows if this guy is being honest with us?
من يدري إن كان هذا الرجل صادقًا أم لا؟
We can't let our guard down.
لا يمكننا أن نتهاون
Stay alert.
تيقظي
Yes.
أمركِ
[Prince Jing'an's Mansion]
[قصر أمير جينغآن]
I'm so sleepy.
أشعر بالنعاس الشديد
Mother-in-law, Father-in-law,
حماتي وحماي
I'm here to pay my respects.
جئت لأقدم لكما التحية
Little beast,
أيها الحيوان الصغير
where are you going?
إلى أين تهرب؟
Darling,
يا زوجتي
bring me my Qinglong Sword!
أحضري لي سيف التنين الأزرق
I must chop this thing into pieces today!
سأقطعه إربًا إربًا اليوم
My Lady.
يا آنستي
Prince Jing'an's Mansion is indeed like hell.
هذا القصر فعلًا أشبه بقصر ملك الموت
Hold it down.
أمسكت به
Should I chop its legs or its waist?
هل أقطع الساق أم الخصر؟
Chop the head first!
اقطع الرأس أولًا
Xie, you're here?
يا ابنة شيه، لقد وصلتِ
Do you like
هل تحبين أكل
duck heads, wings, or legs?
رأس البط أم جناحه أم ساقه؟
Make yourself at home.
لا تتكلفي
Thank you, Mother-in-law.
شكرًا جزيلًا يا حماتي
As their newly wedded daughter-in-law,
دخلتُ المنزل ككنّة جديدة
I wasn't asked to pay my respects
بلا تقديم تحية
or learn any rules?
أو تعلم للقواعد
I have military affairs to attend to.
لدي شؤون عسكرية
I'll go first.
سأغادر أولًا
What military affairs?
أي شؤون عسكرية لديك؟
You must be itching
أنت فقط تشعر برغبة في اللعب مجدداً
to play cards, huh?
وتريد الذهاب للعب الورق، أليس كذلك؟
Darling.
يا زوجتي
I've been at the border for years,
أقضي معظم العام في الحدود
leading troops in battles every day,
وأقود الجنود في المعارك كل يوم
setting an example myself.
وأكون قدوة لهم كل يوم
I've finally returned to the capital. I...
وبعد مشقة كبيرة عدتُ إلى العاصمة
I'll go back to the Northern Border in a few days.
سأعود إلى الحدود الشمالية بعد أيام
As a respectable general,
أنا قائد عسكري محترم
is it really too much to play a few rounds of cards,
لعب الورق ليس أمرا مفرطا، أليس كذلك؟
Xie?
يا فتاة شيه
Just a few rounds.
بضع جولات فقط
I'm telling you,
اسمعني جيدًا
if you lose everything,
إذا خسرتَ كل أموالك
don't even think about coming back home.
فلا تحلم بدخول هذا المنزل مجددا
I won't. I won't.
مستحيل، مستحيل
I won't lose.
لن أخسر، لن أخسر
Xie,
يا فتاة شيه
drink less soup. It's too salty.
لا تشربي الكثير من الحساء، إنه مالح جدا
The Prince used to be a stableboy,
زوجي الأمير كان مجرد سائس خيل
and I am a butcher's daughter.
وأنا أيضًا ابنة جزار
So there are no strict rules in our family.
لذلك لا توجد قواعد كثيرة في بيتنا
That brat,
هذا الفتى المشاغب
why did he marry so many wives?
كيف تزوج كل هؤلاء الزوجات؟
We can't blame him.
لكن لا يمكن لومه على هذا
Since you are here,
بما أنكِ أتيتِ
just stay here with peace of mind.
فابقي هنا براحة
Alright, Mother-in-law.
حسنًا يا حماتي
Drink the soup.
اشربي الحساء، اشربي الحساء
The Xiao family is so strange.
عائلة شياو هذه غريبة جدًا
The Old Prince doesn't look like a general at all.
الأمير العجوز لا يبدو كجنرال أبداً
The Princess is also strange.
والأميرة غريبة أيضاً
As a Buddhist,
كيف لشخص متدين بوذي
how can she eat meat at every meal
أن يرى الدماء بلا مبالاة
and not avoid killing?
ويأكل اللحوم في كل وجبة؟
Your Highness.
يا ولي العهد
The Northern Border is cold.
الحدود الشمالية باردة
I had people skin
لذا أمرت بسلخ جلود
20 white foxes
عشرين ثعلبًا أبيض
to make 2 cloaks.
لصنع معطفين
I'll have them sent to Prince Jing'an's Mansion after court
وسأرسل بهما إلى قصر أمير جينغآن بعد انتهاء مجلس البلاط
as my farewell gift.
لتكونا هدية وداع مني
You are about to return to the Northern Border.
يا ولي العهد، ستعود إلى الحدود الشمالية
We haven't got a chance to catch up with the Old Prince yet.
ولم تتح لنا الفرصة بعد للحديث مع الأمير العجوز
Why don't we find a time to hold a banquet?
ما رأيكم أن نجد وقتاً لإقامة مأدبة؟
Who said I'm going back?
من قال إنني سأعود؟
Are you all hoping
هل تتمنون جميعا
I'll return to the Northern Border soon,
أن أعود إلى الحدود الشمالية مبكرا؟
so you can live a life of pleasure in Jiankang,
لتنعموا أنتم بالحياة المترفة
getting lost in comfort
في جيانكانغ
and never thinking of returning north?
وتنسوا العودة إلى الشمال؟
In that case,
بما أن الأمر كذلك
let me tell you now—
سأخبركم جميعًا اليوم
I'm not returning to the Northern Border for now.
أنني لن أعود إلى الحدود الشمالية في الوقت الحالي
The Empress Dowager is here!
وصلت الإمبراطورة الأرملة
Greetings, Empress Dowager. Greetings, Your Highness.
تحية للإمبراطورة الأرملة تحية لصاحبة الجلالة
You may rise.
يمكنكم الوقوف
Young Lord Xiao was right.
ولي العهد شياو على حق
In the battle at Jiuzhang Plain,
في معركة سهل جيوتشانغ
Northern Qin lost despite outnumbering us.
هُزمت تشين الشمالية رغم كثرة عددها
The Emperor of Northern Qin was furious,
غضب إمبراطور تشين الشمالية بشدة
and the Eagle King, commander of the Black Eagle Army, was demoted.
وقد عزل قائد جيش النسر الأسود، أمير النسر
The Emperor of Northern Qin sent an envoy for peace talks,
ثم أرسل إمبراطور تشين الشمالية مبعوثًا لطلب الصلح
and I agreed.
وقد وافقت
At that time, we will need Young Lord Xiao
وعندها سأكلف ولي العهد شياو
to preside over the peace talks in Jiankang.
برئاسة مفاوضات الصلح في جيانكانغ
Hasn't Young Lord Xiao been focusing on the northern expedition?
أليس ولي العهد شياو مصممًا على الحملة الشمالية؟
I'll do my expedition,
أنا سأواصل حملتي
and you do your talks.
وأنتم واصلوا مفاوضاتكم
These two things can proceed at the same time.
نقاتل ونتفاوض في آن واحد
And we can continue the expedition after the talks.
وبعد انتهاء المفاوضات نعود للقتال
What's wrong with that?
ما المانع في ذلك؟
But what about the Beifu soldiers outside the city?
لكن جنود جيش الشمال خارج المدينة
The Northern Qin peace talks are fraught with danger.
مفاوضات الصلح مع تشين الشمالية مليئة بالمخاطر
In my opinion, during the peace talks,
في رأيي، خلال فترة المفاوضات
the Beifu Army still needs to garrison Jiankang
يجب أن يبقى جيش الشمال مرابطاً في جيانكانغ
to ensure the safety of His Majesty and the Empress Dowager.
لحماية جلالة الإمبراطور والإمبراطورة الأرملة
What do you think, Your Majesty?
ما رأي الإمبراطورة الأرملة؟
Young Lord Xiao,
يا ولي العهد شياو
are you going to leave the army at the Northern Border unattended?
ألن تهتم بجيش الحدود الشمالية؟
Your Majesty, you don't need to worry.
لا داعي للقلق يا صاحبة الجلالة
After the Double Ninth Festival sacrifice,
بعد طقوس عيد تشونغيانغ
my father will immediately return to the Northern Border to command the army.
سيعود والدي فورًا إلى الحدود الشمالية لقيادة الجيش
During the peace talks,
خلال فترة المفاوضات
we will never let the border be taken advantage of by others.
لن نترك أي فرصة للعدو على الحدود
Rest assured, Your Majesty.
يمكن لجلالتكِ الاطمئنان تماما
Prince Jing'an and Young Lord Xiao have thought things through.
أمير جينغآن وولي العهد فكرا في الأمر بملية
That's good.
هذا جيد إذن
I also plan to pray for the sacrificed Beifu soldiers
أنا أخطط أيضًا في احتفال تشونغيانغ أن
at the Double Ninth Ceremony.
نكرم أرواح جنود الشمال الذين ضحوا بحياتهم
The Beifu soldiers stationed outside the city
وعلى جنود الشمال المرابطين خارج المدينة
should also participate.
أن يشاركوا أيضًا
What do you think, Young Lord Xiao?
ما رأيك يا ولي العهد شياو؟
Yes, Your Majesty. Thank you, Your Majesty.
أنا أمتثل للأمر شكرًا على كرم الإمبراطورة الأرملة
If there's nothing else,
إن لم يكن هناك أمر آخر
I'll take my leave.
فأستأذن بالانصراف
Your Majesty,
الإمبراطورة الأرملة
I will see Young Lord Xiao out.
سأذهب لأودع ولي العهد شياو
Wonderful.
هذا رائع
With you in Jiankang,
بوجودك في جيانكانغ
I'm relieved.
أشعر بالاطمئنان
How is she?
كيف حالها؟
She probably wants to poison me to death right now,
ربما ترغب في تسميمي فورا
but for your sake,
ولكن احترامًا لك
she hasn't done it yet.
لم تفعل ذلك حتى الآن
If you dare bully her,
إذا تجرأت على إيذائها
I won't let you off.
فلن أسامحك أبدا
I wouldn't dare.
لا أجرؤ
Young Lord Xiao.
يا ولي العهد شياو
Lady Xie is the beloved daughter of my master.
السيدة شيه هي الابنة المحبوبة لمعلمي
And this marriage was granted by the Empress Dowager.
وهذا الزواج من ترتيب الإمبراطورة الأرملة
Whether you like it or not,
سواء كنت تحبها أم لا
you should treat her well.
عليك أن تعاملها بلطف
Yes.
نعم
Lady Xie is well-educated
ابنة عائلة شيه مثقفة ومهذبة
and gentle.
لطيفة وفاضلة
She is proficient
وتجيد جميع أعمال
in all kinds of women's skills,
التطريز والخياطة
as well as poetry and history.
وتتقن الشعر والكتب الكلاسيكية ببراعة
I will treat her well.
سأحسن معاملتها بكل تأكيد
And I thank the Empress Dowager for granting the marriage.
وأشكر الإمبراطورة الأرملة على ترتيب هذا الزواج
I heard the pear blossom candy at Chengyi Hall in the south of the city
سمعت أن حلوى زهر الكمثرى من متجر تشنغ يي في جنوب المدينة
is especially delicious.
لذيذة جدًا
The ladies in Jiankang are crazy about it.
وفتيات جيانكانغ يتهافتن عليها
Whenever they are in a bad mood, they will buy some to eat.
وكلما ساء مزاج إحداهن، اشترت منها بعضًا
If you're in a bad mood,
إن ساء مزاج ولي العهد شياو
you might as well try it.
فلتجربها
I don't like sweets,
أنا لا أحب الحلويات
I'm not a lady,
ولست فتاة
and I'm in a pretty good mood today.
ومزاجي اليوم جيد
I didn't ask you to eat it.
لم أقصد أن تأكلها
Got it.
فهمت
So annoying.
يا للإزعاج
You have served His Majesty and the Empress Dowager for many years.
لقد خدمت جلالة الإمبراطور والإمبراطورة الأرملة لسنوات
You are the head of the eunuchs in the palace,
وأنت الشخص الأول في القصر
so naturally you are a sensible person.
بالتأكيد تفهم الأمور جيدا
The peace in Southern Ye today
سلام بلادنا يه الجنوبية اليوم
does not depend on good weather,
ليس بسبب الطقس المعتدل
nor on the kindness of the people,
وليس بسبب طيبة أهلها
but on me and the Beifu soldiers guarding the border.
بل لأنني وجنود جيش الشمال حمينا الحدود
The Empress Dowager and I are now at peace
والسلام الحالي بيني وبين الإمبراطورة الأرملة
because we have Prince Qi as the Regent.
هو بفضل وجود سمو الأمير تشي كوصي على العرش
I hope you can remind the Empress Dowager
آمل أن تذكر الإمبراطورة الأرملة
not to follow the disastrous path of Prince Changsha.
بألا تكرر أخطاء أمير تشانغشا
If Prince Qi doesn't even have freedom,
إذا لم يتمتع الأمير تشي حتى بحريته
wouldn't it be a joke to the envoys of Northern Qin?
ألن نصبح أضحوكة أمام مبعوثي تشين الشمالية؟
That's what Young Lord Xiao said.
هذا ما قاله ولي العهد شياو
Your Majesty,
أيتها الإمبراطورة الأرملة
what Young Lord Xiao meant was
يقصد ولي العهد شياو
that the court and the harem should value peace.
أن استقرار البلاط والقصر هو الأهم
He kept the Beifu soldiers in Jiankang
وإبقاؤه جيش الشمال في جيانكانغ
to protect you and His Majesty.
هو لحماية جلالتكِ وجلالة الإمبراطور
He and my brother...
هو وأخي
When have I ever blamed Young Lord Xiao?
متى لُمت ولي العهد شياو؟
Well,
أيتها الفتاة
who taught you the rules?
من الذي علمكِ الآداب؟
My sister and I have been orphans since childhood
أختي وأنا عشنا في شظف منذ الصغر
and had only each other.
ونعتمد على بعضنا البعض
She has neglected her etiquette studies.
لذا قصرتْ في تعلم آداب القصر
Please don't be angry, Your Majesty.
أرجو من جلالتكِ أن تهدئي من غضبك
Never mind.
لا بأس
From now on, you will live with me
من الآن فصاعدًا، ستقيمين معي
in Ziji Palace,
في قصر تسي جي
learning the rules for a few years,
لتتعلمي الآداب لبضع سنوات
so you can find a good match.
ونجد لكِ زواجا مناسبا
Your Majesty...
أيتها الإمبراطورة الأرملة
Since she has neglected her etiquette,
بما أنها تفتقر إلى الآداب
she should be properly taught.
فيجب تعليمها جيدًا
In the future,
في المستقبل
she will become the Grand Princess,
ستصبح الأميرة الكبرى
the face of our Ye.
وتمثل هيبة يه الكبرى
If she is so ignorant of proper etiquette,
إذا كانت تفتقر إلى الآداب هكذا
wouldn't the world laugh at our Ye for having no sense of propriety?
ألن يجعل هذا العالم يسخر من يه الكبرى؟
Not to mention she is already of age.
علاوة على أنها بلغت سن الرشد
You two
أنتما الاثنان
shouldn't live in the same palace anymore anyway.
لا ينبغي أن تعيشا في نفس القصر
He Tian,
خه تيان
take Princess Pingning to the Eastern Palace to pack her things
خذ أميرة بينغنينغ إلى القصر الشرقي لتجمع أغراضها
and move to Ziji Palace immediately.
وانقلوها فورا إلى قصر تسي جي
From today on,
من اليوم فصاعدًا
I
أنا
will personally teach her the rules of the palace.
سأعلمها آداب القصر بنفسي
Yes.
أمرك
Your—
يا صاحبة
Yes, Your Majesty.
أنا أمتثل للأمر
To be taught by you
يشرفني أن أتلقى
is my blessing.
تعليم الإمبراطورة الأرملة
Lejun.
له جيون
What are you still doing here?
سمو الأمير، ما الذي ما زلت تفعله هنا؟
You'll be offering sacrifices
عليك قيادة مراسم تشونغيانغ بدلاً من الإمبراطور
Have you learned all the etiquette and procedures?
هل تعلمت كل الطقوس والإجراءات؟
Fight,
تنافسوا
scramble,
انتزعوا
and struggle.
تقاتلوا
Now that you've stepped into the storm of Jiankang,
فمن دخل دوامة جيانكانغ هذه
who here isn't making moves with their lives at stake
ألا يراهن بحياته؟
while pretending every day that they want nothing?
التظاهر كل يوم بعدم الرغبة في المنافسة
Life is so boring.
يجعل الحياة مملة للغاية
Little fish, tell me.
يا سمكة صغيرة، أخبريني
Will they turn on their own kin first,
هل سيقتل الشقيقان بعضهما أولاً
or will they start fighting among themselves,
أم ينقلب أحدهما على الآخر؟
or will
أو
those who love each other end up killing one another?
أم يقتلان بعضهما بسبب من يحبّان؟
Have you ever thought that this scheme
هل فكرت أن هذه المؤامرة
would ruin Yaoyao's life?
ستدمر حياة جيا يوي بأكملها
Xie Jiayu
شيه جيا يوي بالنسبة لي
is nothing but a stranger to me.
مجرد شخص غريب
Wuyi,
يا وو يي
when you saved me among the refugees back then,
عندما أنقذتني من بين اللاجئين آنذاك
we were also strangers.
كنا أيضًا غريبين عن بعضنا